<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://wangbanban17.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://wangbanban17.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-05-29T21:34:51+00:00</updated><id>https://wangbanban17.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Historian and reader
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Visit to the Bundesagentur für Arbeit</title><link href="https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2023/BA/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visit to the Bundesagentur für Arbeit" /><published>2023-05-19T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-19T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2023/BA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2023/BA/"><![CDATA[<p>For many international students in Germany, German bureaucracy is nightmare. Bundesagentur in Heidelberg seems to be an exception though.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life" /><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[light from a nightmare?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">《史達林與歐洲的命運》：一篇書評</title><link href="https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2023/naimark/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="《史達林與歐洲的命運》：一篇書評" /><published>2023-02-08T17:26:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-08T17:26:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2023/naimark</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2023/naimark/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="book-review">Book review</h1>

<p><img src="https://assets.matters.news/embed/de3fc62e-525a-4067-9afe-02068b989c43.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="https://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674238770">出版信息</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>我們或許忘記了，世界上有多少事並非受制於強權，又有多少人有著自己的意志。—— A.J.P. Taylor</p>
</blockquote>

<p>看到這本標題爲《Stalin and the Fate of Europe: The Postwar Struggle for Sovereignty》的書，我的第一反應是：「啊，檔案基礎上的大國博弈和獨裁者心理分析麼？不過是一位著名學者的作品呢。」翻到題記竟是經常被當作「民粹式史學家」的 Taylor 的這句話，纔覺並非如此簡單。身處東亞的我們或許比較清楚，第二次世界大戰之後又過了十數年，新的政治秩序方逐漸穩定下來：國共戰爭、朝鮮戰爭、印度支那戰爭甚至七十年代的越南戰爭，都是二戰後重劃東亞政治版圖的集中體現。第二次世界大戰在世界上的很多地方，都不過是一連串戰爭中相對較大的一場，在一些地方（比如西亞）甚至不如後來更嚴重的戰爭。但在歐洲，敘事似乎很簡單和粗線條：在柏林被攻克後，似乎就衹有華盛頓和莫斯科不斷瓜分歐洲的勢力範圍，最終鐵幕降下，歐洲分裂成東西兩大陣營。走過歐洲各國的博物館，對二戰結束到冷戰開始的這段時間描述往往集中在如何重建家園、如何審判納粹和國內內奸、如何重建國家主權或者被（主要是蘇聯）霸權國家操控。這種表達大概不能算是完全離譜，但也是極大簡化了問題。美蘇在歐洲不同地區投入的精力相當不平衡。具體到每一個國家，站在 1945 年，它們的命運未必是註定的；整個歐洲也未必一定會走向分裂和冷戰。我們現在看待這段時間的角度，很大程度上是因爲我們天然被「劇透」了。</p>

<p>而身爲美國人的作者奈馬克，希望提醒讀者（當然首先是美國讀者）注意更重要的三個要素：史達林的個人政策、歐洲人的主動性和即將到來的冷戰。爲此，他選擇了七個地區不同、背景不同、發展方向及結果亦不相同的案例，試圖呈現這三個要素在各種案例中的多樣性以及彼此拉鋸的過程。按作者原話：</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>They demonstrate that postwar Europe was in a state of flux: Allied armies evacuated occupied territories; alliances were redefined; local politics mattered. Elections were crucial and political leadership meant a lot. [24]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>考慮到奈馬克的方法論，我認爲對本書的評價不可避免地要回到對這七個案例的細緻討論中，看作者是否在史料允許的情況下，確實證明了史達林並無既定不變的方針，是否充分表現了歐洲各國的能動性，是否足夠聯繫起更大局勢和後來發展。</p>

<hr />

<p>下面展開討論這七個案例：</p>

<p>1. 丹麥•博爾赫姆島（1945-6），這座島嶼因其介於瑞典、德國、波蘭之間的波羅的海出口位置，戰略地位很早就被蘇聯重視。二戰結束前蘇軍對該島大舉進攻，試圖讓島上德軍降蘇以便長期控制。但經過丹麥與蘇聯的談判，蘇軍於 1946 年 4 月撤出該島，丹麥則與蘇聯簽訂貿易協定幫助蘇聯恢復經濟，並保證英美軍隊不得踏足該島。奈馬克主張，斯大林的目標從一開始軍事上長期控制該島，逐漸轉變爲以在島上駐軍爲威脅，要求駐在丹麥的英軍撤離。蘇軍並未試圖在該島上施行蘇聯體制或清算納粹協力者，他們雖然與當地民衆有所摩擦，但在更大程度上與當地保持着純然民事上的接觸。當地民衆與政府也並非一邊倒地反感蘇軍，甚至丹麥王儲都一度訪問該島慰問蘇聯駐軍：史達林因此得以藉此在撤軍前獲取更多道義上的和經濟上的利益。但在親蘇派失利丹麥大選、蘇軍得以控制其他交通要道的基礎上，丹麥外交力量的反覆斡旋成功說服史達林和莫洛托夫（蘇聯外長），以貿易合作換取撤軍。奈馬克看到史達林希望構建一片中立緩衝地帶的想法，而丹麥外交的努力也符合史達林的期待。</p>

<p>這一章作爲全書開頭，很大程度上試圖打破對蘇佔區的刻板印象：奈馬克的描述十分緩和，蘇軍就像是一批長期寄居但自己也不清楚要待多久的客人，在這裏和主人們跳舞喝酒。但覈查引文就會發現，作者使用史料以俄文和英文爲主，丹麥文檔案和作品則鮮有使用（或許是因爲語言限制？）。我因此雖然並不會懷疑哥本哈根政府的外交策略（因爲僅有的一本丹麥文作品是關於高層外交的，還有俄文譯本），但對當地民衆究竟如何看待這件事，卻有進一步的問題。當地民衆和知識人如何看待丹麥與德國在戰爭中的某種合作，以及當地和哥本哈根媒體如何報道蘇聯駐軍事宜，都是問題。本章結尾，奈馬克描述了島上的蘇聯紀念碑遺蹟和丹麥與俄國對島上禁止外國駐軍的「君子協定」。我也因此好奇，這些遺蹟對當地的集體記憶又有多大意義。爲什麼 90 年代以後丹麥仍然遵守著這條君子協定，而美國是否又想過打破它呢？另外，史達林在本章中很大程度上被他的外長莫洛托夫搶戲，作者有時候似乎默認著莫洛托夫的文字背後有史達林的意志，有時候又覺得莫洛托夫是以自己的方針處理外交（這點我將在之後提及）。當然本章在全書中也屬於相對較有系統的一部分。</p>

<p>2. 阿爾巴尼亞的獨立（1944-8）。二戰以後強大的南斯拉夫一直試圖將阿爾巴尼亞吸收爲自己的加盟國，以擴展自己在整個南巴爾幹的勢力範圍，而並不重視阿爾巴尼亞的史達林對此本來沒有意見。阿爾巴尼亞內部則對如何應對北方強鄰十分矛盾：南斯拉夫領袖鐵托支持的佐治（Koçi Xoxe）主張親善南斯拉夫甚至直接併入其中，以抗衡南方的資本主義希臘王國。領袖霍查（Enver Hoxha）則是民族主義者，他先尋求在南斯拉夫內同出一族的科索沃人的支持，以圖在可能統一的大南斯拉夫中謀得更大話語權；在鐵托試圖支持佐治奪權時，霍查先是訪問莫斯科，拉進自己與蘇聯的關係並隱隱傳達對鐵托的不滿，刺激史達林與鐵托的矛盾；又利用反南斯拉夫派大人物詩俾魯（Nako Spiru）之死和蘇聯駐阿爾巴尼亞專家等問題爲藉口將蘇南矛盾逐漸挑明，然後兩面用力，既維持南阿關係使得本國能有安全保障，又效忠蘇聯以防鐵托用佐治取代自己。蘇南交惡後，霍查更有了徹底切割南斯拉夫的機會：他得以成爲蘇聯在南巴爾幹的橋頭堡和可信盟友（並因此壓過了另一個南巴爾幹社會主義國家保加利亞一頭），並以「鐵托主義叛徒」的罪名處決了政敵佐治，鞏固了將持續近四十年的個人統治，並也開始了自己不斷更換依附對象的時代：霍查將在蘇共二十大後聯合毛澤東與蘇聯決裂，並在毛與美國接近時又指責毛背叛馬列主義。</p>

<p>這一章相比上一章，重要角色要更多：奈馬克花了將近一整節來講述史達林和鐵托如何逐漸走向決裂，以便讀者理解霍查如何利用二者矛盾，並腳踏兩隻船直到最終站在蘇聯一邊。但核心仍然放在史達林和霍查兩人身上。在史達林角度，奈馬克成功描繪了他從一開始輕視阿爾巴尼亞，到利用阿爾巴尼亞來抵抗鐵托的過程。霍查在本章中也有從「試圖在大南斯拉夫內爲本民族爭取更高地位」到堅決抵抗南斯拉夫的轉變。如果說要在本章中挑出最重要的問題，就是蘇聯、阿爾巴尼亞以外的史料很少。考慮到貝爾格萊德檔案在 1999 年被炸後保存不佳，我們無法苛責作者未能使用塞爾維亞的檔案；但在敘述霍查與保加利亞、希臘共產黨人的聯動一節中，卻衹有霍查的聲音，保加利亞和希臘的檔案則幾乎沒有。我可以看到本章作者頗具野心地想把霍查的運作放在整個南巴爾幹地緣政治的範疇之下，但不得不說他劃定的範圍實在太大，絕非一章可以收錄了。除此以外，本章的水平要高於上一章。</p>

<p>3. 芬蘭爭取政治獨立（1944-8）。二戰期間站在德國一邊的芬蘭，在戰後幾乎被英美放棄，似乎註定要成爲蘇聯的附庸國，而史達林也派出深受信任的日丹諾夫（Andrei Aleksandrovich Zhdanov）代表督管芬蘭，試圖在當地推行「人民民主主義」。那麼芬蘭爲何最終仍得以維持憲政民主呢？奈馬克認爲有兩個重要因素：（1）審時度勢、知道如何討好史達林的同時維持國家獨立性的「老芬蘭」（Old Finns）保守派；（2）史達林和日丹諾夫都對始終扶不起的芬蘭共產黨十分失望。在芬蘭共產黨始終無法擴大政治影響力的情況下，一直和蘇聯保持溝通的老政客巴錫基维（Juho Kusti Paasikivi）一面積極與社會民主黨合作，一面在戰犯審判、割地賠款、不參與馬歇爾計劃（Marshall Plan）等問題上向蘇聯讓步。芬蘭共產黨則既受制於蘇聯佔領軍的政策，自己也無法提升民望，在大選中節節失利。相比於將芬蘭變成社會主義國家，史達林首先考慮的是讓芬蘭無法再次威脅蘇聯（尤其是列寧格勒）。因此，在反覆談判後他認定，與蘇聯有漫長不設防邊境的芬蘭在被剝奪大片領土後已是安全的夥伴，於是順水推舟促成了盟軍與芬蘭的和平協定。就此，緊鄰蘇聯並曾被蘇聯長期駐軍的芬蘭，竟奇跡般地在一批舊政客帶領下從蘇聯人手上贏得了獨立自主。</p>

<p>這是相對單薄的一章，不僅因爲現實情勢相對簡單，牽涉人物不如前兩章多，更因爲作者幾乎沒有直接使用芬蘭方面的檔案材料：僅有的部分芬蘭史料轉引自一本芬蘭人寫的芬蘭通史。老芬蘭政客與社會民主黨之間的溝通未能充分展現，使奈馬克關於老芬蘭政客的動機猜測頗成問題。考慮到芬蘭檔案史料相對開放，這很可能又是因爲作者的語言侷限：我們當因此質疑作者爲何要選擇一個自己無法直接閱讀其語言的領域了。當然，蘇聯方面的觀點變化更清晰一些，但奈馬克似乎又沒有仔細區分哪些是史達林的觀點，哪些是日丹諾夫的，哪些又是日丹諾夫揣度史達林想法後提出的。綜合來看，本章可能更適合毫不熟悉相關史事的讀者淺嚐輒止，有意深入者敬請直接閱讀相關人物的研究。</p>

<p>4. 意大利的戰後選舉（1948）。雖然蘇聯未曾駐軍意大利，但戰後的意大利共產黨及其領袖托里亞蒂（Parmiro Togliatti）在國內威望很高，史達林因此不希望意共武裝奪取政權，而是與現政府合作並逐步將該國轉爲社會主義。本章的核心是意大利戰後，意共和基督教民主黨如何反覆調整策略，而英美和蘇聯又如何不同程度干預意大利的選舉。托里亞蒂一直壓抑黨內激進派以和基督教民主黨總理德加斯佩里（Alcido De Gasperi）合作，但後者 1947 年初訪美後堅定的親美政策和 5 月解散內閣驅除意共閣員等動作，讓意共、蘇聯和試圖在意大利獲得更多話語權的南斯拉夫，都一度籌劃武裝運動。但隨着蘇南對立，史達林又轉而支持托里亞蒂的溫和傾向，鼓勵他在 1948 年 4 月大選中聯合社民黨等中產階級和中左翼勢力，搞一場捷克斯洛伐克式的政治化紅色風潮。在捷克斯洛伐克事件後深憂意大利步其後塵的英美也大開宣傳機器，從經濟威脅到拍攝反蘇影片，再到天主教會的深度介入，甚至動用早已定居美國的意裔人士名義給意民眾寫信來影響結果。意共在大選中失利讓激進派再次籌劃武裝運動，並在托里亞蒂於同年 7 月遇刺重傷後發動大罷工，意政府也防備著可能爆發的內戰。但蘇聯反對事態進一步升級，復出政壇的托里亞蒂也迅速採取冷靜政策。意共就此再也無法在全國政治舞臺上合法奪權，而蘇聯也對西歐共產黨整體失望了。</p>

<p>這章內容很豐富，論述也很深入，也是筆者認爲最能體現本書研究方法的一章。當然這也可能是因爲這是本書第一個大量運用本地史料的章節。托里亞蒂被塑造成一位爲保證國家和平寧可犧牲黨派利益的革命者，始終利用自己的威信維持著共產黨的地位並保證激進派不致發動暴動。史達林的決策方向則很複雜：他並不喜歡托里亞蒂，但又不得不依賴後者的威望；他既希望意大利能發生捷克斯洛伐克一樣的社會主義改變，又憚於布拉格事件後英美的強硬反應，更在晚些時候擔心鐵托能借意大利武裝運動掀起更大風浪。德加斯佩里則用精妙的政治操作，一面倒向美國支持本國經濟，一面在國內利用蘇聯威脅和與托里亞蒂的良好關係謀取自己利益最大化。得益於豐富的檔案和報刊史料，奈馬克成功描述了美英、教會、基督教民主黨、意共和蘇聯等各方在不同時間的政治操作變化，並且將意大利事務與同時期的世界格局成功聯繫起來。唯一稍顯不足的是，德加斯佩里相關的材料似乎主要出自關於他的傳記，而並非直接利用檔案，是個遺憾。</p>

<p>5. 柏林封鎖（1948-9）。這是七章內容中（美國）普通讀者可能最爲熟悉的一段史事，也是奈馬克本人研究的專業領域。傳統敘述中，蘇聯軍事封鎖柏林要將崇尚自由的西柏林人餓死，而英勇的美英飛行員通過空運救助了西柏林陷入饑荒的普通德國人。而奈馬克努力強調，在傳統敘述中德國人尤其是柏林人的角色被大幅低估了，而史達林也不是鐵了心從頭開始就要餓死德國人這麼簡單。戰後蘇聯和法國希望儘量榨取德國的工業產能與資源來彌補本國戰爭期間的嚴重損失，而英美則更希望德國經濟迅速自立，以降低本國駐軍和資助的預算。對史達林來說，一個統一但在經濟政治上弱化的德國要比一個分裂但軍事經濟完全恢復的德國更符合蘇聯利益。他相信，衹要德國是中立而非完全倒向西方，蘇聯在大陸上的強大軍力就能保證德國如芬蘭一般居於中立。英美法三國佔領區的貨幣改革打碎了史達林的計劃。 他嘗試用外交手段阻止西方陣營失敗後，便逐漸開始審查東西方之間的出版品和物資往來、劫持政敵等手段，以脅迫西方就範，但當時未有封鎖進出路徑或禁飛的打算。而美軍此時就已經加強空運，預防可能的徹底封鎖；並繼續推動西德地區的議會選舉等建政舉措。史達林試圖把西方打成「分裂主義者」（splitters）、鼓吹「實現德國統一」來吸引德國民眾，但西德貨幣改革帶來的經濟成功，進一步撕裂了蘇聯與西方的差距。封鎖西柏林應被看作是蘇聯德國政策的一環，他們無意也沒有令西柏林陷入饑荒，而是因應形勢讓封鎖或松或緊，尤其是希望讓德國人和柏林人認清，誰纔是柏林的主宰。西方雖然開始了柏林空運和對蘇佔東德地區的物資禁運，但仍被迫坐到了談判桌前。</p>

<p>本章成功的部分在於呈現了上至西柏林市長洛伊特（Ernst Reuter）下至普通柏林市民對封鎖的情緒變化：奈馬克利用了不少普通人和文化人的書信和檔案，來還原當時的社會風向：他們逐漸苦於蘇聯的攔路審查、沒收西德馬克和應對抗議時的暴行，又利用東西柏林貨幣不對等，運輸東柏林高價值產品來賺取西德馬克。在蘇聯要求西柏林人「到蘇佔區註冊」以獲得生活物資補給時，已經看到英美空運的西柏林人祇有少數前去註冊，而多數則開始協助英美空軍投送物資。西柏林市長洛伊特看到英美試圖建立一個西德政府時，又擔心英美將放棄西柏林這片飛地專注於西方各邦，因而在1948 年 9 月 9 日發表了著名的「國會演說」，呼籲國際社會支持西柏林，並呼籲東西柏林市民向蘇軍示威。這種類似道德脅迫的政治舉措引來擔心蘇軍直接出兵西柏林的美軍不滿，但美軍也無法公開批評西柏林人的行為。柏林人的壓力、遭禁運的蘇佔東德面臨經濟困難、英美擔憂對立引發暴動或戰爭，多方力量最終推動莫斯科和華盛頓磋商化解危機。而史達林的觀點變化脈絡，在全章則並不清晰。奈馬克或許是發現自己的敘述主線略顯破碎，於是在本章結語中重新勾勒了史達林對西柏林和西德民衆心理的多次誤讀，這倒是很值得今日的讀者欣賞一番。總而言之，本章非常符合「the Fate of Europe」的副標題，但 Stalin 含量不足。僅論史料運用和敘述水準，也是上佳的一章。</p>

<p>6. 波蘭工人黨領導人哥慕烏卡（Władysław Gomułka）與史達林的恩怨（1944–9）。這一章主要討論波蘭工人黨內部的路線闘爭。戰前史達林就很不喜歡偏向托洛茨基派（Trotskyism）的波蘭共產黨，並在 1938 年將大量波共領導人送進古拉格，因此二戰期間重組的波蘭工人黨多數都忠於史達林。老資格共產黨人哥慕烏卡偶然逃過了 1938 年大清洗，並在德國佔領波蘭時重回波蘭工人黨，但他深知，在戰爭期間史達林對波蘭也沒做什麼好事。史達林雖在工人黨中扶持同樣老資格的別盧特（Bolesław Bierut），但政治基礎深厚的哥慕烏卡威信仍一時無兩，他實幹的風格也與史達林實用主義的波蘭政策很接近。但哥慕烏卡還是民族主義者。他發展出了一套所謂「通往社會主義的波蘭路線」：他希望讓波蘭人用波蘭的方法做事，而非唯莫斯科馬首是瞻；他像標準的波蘭民族主義者那樣反對猶太人在波蘭工人黨中佔據重要地位，即使這些人多是史達林的親信；他用民族主義式的宣傳提升工人黨的公信力，這在共產國際和正統派共產黨人之中引發爭議；他在蘇南衝突中始終希望做和事佬，引發史達林和親蘇派的不滿。最終導致他被罷黜的是 1948 年他對猶太共產主義的批評：史達林在此時雖然已經開始警惕東歐共產黨中的猶太人，但也不願看到波蘭工人黨中佔比很大的親蘇猶太領導人被哥慕烏卡迅速打敗。而哥慕烏卡過早公開了這場矛盾，這就逼着史達林站在他的對立面：8–9 月，隨着別盧特訪蘇，對哥慕烏卡的總清算開始了。他被貼上「民族主義」「右傾」「獨裁」「在宗派主義與極端機會主義間反覆」等罪名，但因他在波蘭的威望和非猶太人身份，史達林不便直接處死他，而試圖說服他改弦更張，服從工人黨的親蘇路線；同時以同樣的罪名審判清洗他的親信。見哥慕烏卡不屈服，親史達林的別盧特下令逮捕了他，雖仍礙於他的地位而未審判或處死他，但還是將他軟禁在家，直至三年半後纔釋放。</p>

<p>本章細節豐富，正文全在利用蘇聯和波蘭的回憶錄、檔案和公開文本梳理史事，並在敘述中牽涉戰前波蘭共產黨、共產國際大會等其他相關史事。到結語，奈馬克纔提出了嚴肅的問題：爲什麼哥慕烏卡在清洗中倖存，而波蘭工人黨在史達林死後又如何逐漸走回了哥慕烏卡的道路，直到哥慕烏卡於 1956 年重回政治舞臺。他試圖呈現，即使在被蘇聯牢牢拴住的波蘭，當地共產黨人也可戴着鐐銬有限度地挑戰莫斯科的利益。這樣的題目正如奈馬克本人所說，在南斯拉夫體現得最爲明顯。而波蘭則是問題繁多，但每一個問題都無法單獨討論。總之。本章大體可說是優秀的歷史敘事，但略顯零散。</p>

<p>7. 戰後奧地利的主權獨立（1944–9）。奧地利雖然被認定是「納粹的第一個受害國」但戰後卻像德國一樣被四大國分別佔領。史達林在奧地利有多級目標：最好能讓奧地利變成「人民民主」的東歐式國家，一定不能讓奧地利直接倒向西方陣營，並必須保證蘇聯能在奧地利穩定駐軍至少一段時間以維持其在羅馬尼亞和匈牙利駐軍。史達林頗有頭腦地搬請德高望重的左翼領袖勒納（Karl Renner）領導一個有中右翼參與但整體左傾的臨時政府，很快維持住了奧地利政局並得到西方承認。但蘇軍在奧糟糕的軍紀，加之 1945 年國會選舉共產黨表現不利，都讓史達林很快放棄了將奧地利拉入東方陣營的想法，轉而控制奧地利蘇佔區的石油、火車工業等經濟部門，以便恢復東歐經濟和加強蘇聯在奧的硬實力。但奧地利戰後數年的選舉中，不僅共產黨始終無法得到 6% 的選篇，甚至前納粹成員都得到更多的票數，這也說明奧地利民衆在戰後的政治傾向，與美英和蘇聯的考慮均不相同。美英均希望迅速從奧地利撤軍，蘇聯也開始逐漸不關注奧地利，但蘇聯控制的奧地利經濟部門、奧地利「去納粹化」進程不順、法國和蘇聯要求的賠款問題等，都延緩了和平條約的簽訂。1948 年以後東歐倒向蘇聯，讓美國國防部更不願撤出奧地利，與美國外交部產生矛盾；蘇聯則害怕從奧地利撤軍後，已經撕破臉皮的南斯拉夫會乘機威脅有蘇聯駐軍的匈牙利和羅馬尼亞；斯大林死後，赫魯曉夫和莫洛托夫在奧地利問題上又意見相左。這場談判桌上的拉鋸戰最終到 1955 年纔告結束，剛剛建立的華沙公約組織讓蘇聯有理由常駐羅馬尼亞和匈牙利，而新的奧地利總理又對蘇聯讓步，並許諾本國的永久中立。奧地利最終得以在永久中立的基礎上結束十年佔領期。</p>

<p>本章並不好讀，雖然德文檔案材料豐富，但因爲史達林並不太重視奧地利，奈馬克使用的大量俄文材料都來自赫魯曉夫時代，其中意識形態的變化是否帶來記載上的偏差，奈馬克沒有提醒讀者注意。作者成功傳達了自己的觀點：奧地利的命運似乎一面因本國民衆的多次大選而很早敲定，另一方面又因爲美蘇內部的政治路線闘爭久久懸而未決。但或許是因爲意大利、柏林和波蘭三章珠玉在前，這個敘事略顯混亂，分析問題也淺嚐輒止的章節就顯得平淡了。</p>

<hr />

<p>我花費大量篇幅逐章討論的目的之一在於呈現本書的一大問題：各個案例研究的聯繫不足。這可能是所有以案例研究爲方法的歷史研究的宿命，但也一定程度上受限於作者的選例。他有意選取了一些在美國讀者看來並不那麼熟悉的國家和時期，這當然有助於賣書、讓作者相對方便地避開學術爭論最激烈的領域而投入自己的研究，但也讓這些國際性並不太強的案例（尤其是前三章）彼此間的聯繫並不那麼清楚。讀者可以看到蘇聯和南斯拉夫的衝突在阿爾巴尼亞、意大利、奧地利和波蘭事件的背後都起到了一定作用；但受限於作者對一些當地史料使用不足，我們並不太容易看到這些國家如何理解、適應和主動利用「國際大環境」來爲自己謀利（霍查除外）。</p>

<p>另一個令我不安的問題在於本書的主角史達林。在奈馬克的理解中，史達林外交政策並非全然理性、一貫，也不成系統。同時，即使是英法以外的其他歐洲各國，其內部的各方勢力也並非唯美蘇之一馬首是瞻。奈馬克試圖塑造這樣的史達林形象：他並不像傳統美國敘述中那樣，努力要把蘇聯模式推得越遠越好；他對不少東歐共產黨人並無好感，也在一些共產黨內部「踩一捧一」；他雖然不怕對抗，但在（他認爲）無意義的對抗上也不吝讓步。這個形象大體成立了，但在各章具體敘述中，史達林似乎更像是在每處要衝下小棋，而不是在下大棋：在給霍查回信時，他似乎並沒有關注同一時期的意大利；在威脅哥慕烏卡的同時，似乎柏林和維也納並不在他的視野中。這可能也是因爲作者使用的史料來源相對著重於個案。奈馬克在序言中曾指出，莫洛托夫等人的聲音背後都有著史達林的影子；但他在具體行文時，有時會直接把莫洛托夫、日丹諾夫等人的觀點拿來當作史達林的意見（如芬蘭一章），這也在一定程度上把本書副標題的「史達林」變成了「莫斯科」。在這點上，奧地利的部分因爲有著史達林和赫魯曉夫路線的不同，反而讓我們更清楚看到哪些是史達林的意見，哪些是蘇聯上層的共識。</p>

<p>這兩個大問題背後都是史料問題。考慮到本書終歸並非是專門個案的深入討論，而更像是一種半學術半普及的作品，我並不期待作者在非本人專精領域（德語、俄語世界）外給出什麼突破性的成果。奈馬克在自己能讀懂一手史料的四章中整體做得很好，而在丹麥、阿爾巴尼亞和芬蘭三例上則很明顯受到語言限制，史料集中在少數翻譯成其他語言的文集裏。在這種情況下，我期待奈馬克在序言就自我剖白，承認自己在選取史料的層面受什麼樣的侷限，而不是讓有心爬梳尾注的無聊讀者（比如我）發現後再來檢討問題。這再次提醒我等學史者，語言始終是研究任何問題上不能短缺的一塊木板。</p>

<p>奈馬克的大結語有很強的當代政治指向：他討論了歐盟對當下俄羅斯佔領克里米亞的反應，並認爲歐盟領導人的措施太軟。似乎他在用本書告訴歐洲人，「你們的先人面對不可一世的史達林都能爭得不同程度的自由空間。」對這種政治指向，還請各位讀者自行考量。</p>

<hr />

<p>我會向所有非冷戰史專業的朋友推薦本書。這本書至少在一點上非常成功：奈馬克成功讓讀者認清，那些事後看來再不可避免、趨勢再明顯不過的事件，其發生之前都可能有多種可能性，其演進的過程都非常複雜。當下的歷史學者，不敢說每個人都會努力擁抱和鍾愛這種複雜性，但至少都不會排斥之。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reading" /><category term="reading" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Book review]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">anchoring monumental landscape in Delphi</title><link href="https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2022/utrecht/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="anchoring monumental landscape in Delphi" /><published>2022-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2022/anchoring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2022/utrecht/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="anchoring-the-monumental-landscape">Anchoring the Monumental Landscape:</h1>

<p>Early Roman inscriptions contextualised in the Hellenistic sanctuary of Apollo Pythios</p>

<h2 id="preamble">preamble</h2>

<p>This is the first in-person academic conference I’ve participated in during the COVID times, and the last country I visited before the pandemic was the Netherlands. The last time I was at Utrecht Centraal, my German sounded like Dutch; and now, my Dutch bears a strong German accent. The pandemic has changed so much our world that everyone is anxious to find new stabilities and rules for living, but the old anchors may need serious reconsiderations.</p>

<h2 id="delphi-as-the-spatial-testimony">Delphi as the spatial testimony</h2>

<p>So much for contemporary issues and now let’s scale back twenty three centuries, towards the early second century before the Christian era, another time period when great changes took place. Entrance and Involvement of the Romans in the Eastern Mediterranean Area gave birth to “a change for a millenium” which permanently transformed the area. The main playground of our workshop, Delphi, was definitely a crucial space within this transformation. All the major changes brought by the external powers tend to bring materialisation of new power, structure and newly constructed memory in this space, which witnessed all kinds of physical testimonies to previous glories. Romans were, perhaps, just a new dominant power initially, and only later did the Delphians know the dominance would last long. <em>This presentation brings ideas on how the new power, the Romans took the Hellenistic sanctuary and injected their practice in this Greek landmark.</em></p>

<h2 id="start-with-a-statue">Start with a statue</h2>

<p>Let’s start with perhaps the most famous Roman monument in Delphi, the pillar of Aemilius Paulus, located at the front terrace of the Apollo temple. According to Plutarch, in -168 after his victory against Perseus in Pydna, L. Aemilius Paulus visited Delphi and saw a rectangular grand pillar in white marble, on which a golden statue of Perseus was to be placed. Paulus »gave orders that his own statue should be set there, for it was proper that the conquered should make room for their conquerors.«<d-footnote>Plut. Aem. 28.4. Polybius said there were multiple monuments, but archaeologists during the Grande Fouille only identified one monument that could be Paulus’s.</d-footnote></p>

<p>The pillar was divided into three parts: an orthostatic base, the shaft of the pillar with rosette decorations, and the entablature with an architrave, a frieze, and a cornice. While in Plutarch’s words we may assume the upper parts were later taken down with a new statue, archaeologists have found no trace for that: there was, according to multiple archaeologists, never a frieze for Perseus, and we see clear unity of execution between the shaft and the entablature.<d-footnote>Jacquemin &amp; Laroche 1982, 210 stands still here. </d-footnote> It’s thus safe to say, that the majority of the pillar was made with Roman themes. But there are in fact at least four pillars in similar shapes standing in this crowded area, and decorations like rosettes were also not unknown on other pillars. A contemporary visitor might say »Ehh, another pillar« when facing it.</p>

<p>The orthostatic base and its inscription pose questions beyond philology. Claude Vatin and earlier archaeologists all mention that »it’s certain that a Greek inscription existed before the Latin text«, though very difficult to decipher. While I think it goes too far to suggest that what Paulus saw was only this base, it is a fact that this base was reused from a Greek offering and the offering must have been massive given its size, likely to be royal: after all, to reuse something as a massive monument, you need a large original. We know many cases of reuse, but this is definitely the largest. The Latin text is also unusual from a classical perspective: as Apollo was not mentioned, it was not a »dedicatory text« in strict sense. But other Delphic pillars nearby also normally have no dedications, in contrast, they usually have honorific inscriptions at the most visible part of the shaft. Here, the Latin text only says that the consul »took from King Perseus and Macedonians«. The object, though omitted, is obvious, as long as THE AUDIENCE READS LATIN. As of now, the most convincing proposal about the pillar is, for me, that its base was captured and the upper parts were added subsequently following surrounding examples; but there are also new elements: the new language inaccessible to local visitors, large-scale reuse, and a frieze with lavish decorations.</p>

<h2 id="statements">Statements</h2>

<p>The pillar of Aemilius Paulus shows multiple layers of phenomena that I’d like to discuss in today’s talk. It was a reused monument, and the original scale enabled the reuse. It was erected in an area full of similar objects, reinforcing the monumental landscape of the terrace in front of the temple. And as I will discuss later, it would eventually be used following a Delphic pattern of reusing old monuments to carry later inscriptions of various nature. On the levels of monument, landscape and practice, we see clear similarities between this pillar and other dedications in the Hellenistic sanctuary of Apollo, but also new elements that were never seen in earlier times.</p>

<p>This links to the main topic of our workshop, the practice of anchoring with previous existing objects and patterns of practice. »When in Delphi, do as what other people did here«. I appropriate the proverb to describe the Roman practice in its earlier stage. As Ineke Sluiter mentioned in the founding essay of the project, imitation and appropriation play a key role in the anchoring innovation as it facilitates the understanding and usage of the new by putting it in old frameworks.</p>

<p>But in contrast with previous dominant powers like the Macedonians and the Aitolians, the coming of the Romans was met with more active responses from the Delphians, who were both actively exploiting the Roman influence in order to get rid of the Aitolian dominance, and fearing the political instability and the potential disasters as many anti-Roman Greek powers, Perseus included, also tried to benefit from the prestige of Apollo Pythios’ sanctuary. Therefore, the early second century before Christ witnessed not consecutive impositions of Roman monuments, but a mutual honour-favour system. In this way, I hope to render more agency to the Delphians and the Amphictiony when proper. Notice, in this period Delphi also underwent significant Athenian and Pergamene influence, topics that I’ll discuss in other chapters of my dissertation but not here.</p>

<h2 id="three-levels-of-anchoring">Three levels of anchoring</h2>

<p>The transformation of the sanctuary’s landscape can be understood in three levels, as the two parts we have already seen from the Pillar.</p>

<p>First, monuments that existed prior to the coming of the Romans were re-used, at various scales, for Roman purposes. This, I repeat, was not exclusively done by the Romans, but in many cases by locals and by the erectors of the monument.</p>

<p>Second, erection of monuments for Roman purposes changes the surrounding landscape, but at the same time should adhere to the previous look and could not be too out-of-context.</p>

<p>Third, the practice of erecting monuments for Roman purposes largely follows earlier Hellenistic practice, that is, keeping monuments at the most prominent space open to further texts, but to a certain extent related to Romans.</p>

<p>Now I’d like to expand the three points with selected examples. Notice, that while we have 24 monuments that were related to the Romans in the period -190 to -31, only a few can be securely located or found <em>in situ</em>. Like the pillar, what we know are usually its contemporary form, and the area to which it would have been erected. Therefore, a very detailed visual tour is, while very charming, infeasible. Even so, certain interpretations could be made on a not-so-micro-level. I would also like to hear from you whether you think my interpretations are too wild.</p>

<h2 id="monuments-reused-for-roman-purposes">Monuments reused for Roman purposes</h2>

<p>First, about reused monuments for Romans.</p>

<p>We are talking about two kinds of reuse: the first is complete capture and repurposing, as we saw in the case of Paulus’s pillar.</p>

<p>According to Dominika Grzesik’s painstaking calculations, there were 24 statues for Roman officials mentioned in literary and epigraphic sources during the period between -190 and -31, but we found only 15 that could be traced on stone, and in two cases we know from proxenia decrees that there would have been a statue somewhere, only not found.</p>

<p>At least in three cases were material taken from other monuments, its original text erased in order to bear new Roman texts: notice that there were only six confirmed cases in Delphi for the entire Hellenistic period, so to some extent such Roman reuse is neither too banal nor too innovative. In all the three cases, the size of the original block is decisive to the size of the new staute. An orthostatic base from the famous ex-voto of Daochos was taken from the Thessalian treasury to the south of the sacred way, and a Latin dedication was inscribed under the name of Q. Minucius Rufus the legatus in -107. Notice that the Latin ligature »Ph« and the »V« in place for »Y«, both symbolising a certain Greekness in the process of inscribing a text foreign to Delphi. The base would later be further reused by a proxenia decree for a Leukios Tillios or Lucius Tullius (<em>SGDI</em> II 2688) at least twenty years later (a better date could be expected when <em>CID</em> 5.2 is published, fingers crossed.). Then, the Delphians would clearly have a say over the statue for the Roman legatus, as an abbreviated decree for L. Tullius L. f. fits well on a statue for a Roman official.</p>

<p>The second kind of reuse is to take an available space while not changing its original purposes. What stays in my mind is that some documents rendering Roman authority were inscribed on important buildings or dedications within the sanctuary. The original meaning of the building, therefore, is crucial to the disposition of the new text. A very visible case is the <em>senatus Consultum</em> arbitrating the dispute between Athenian and Isthmian dionysiac artists (<em>FD</em> III 2.70). The long <em>SC</em> in -112 was in favour of the Athenians, so the latter naturally inscribed the long text onto their most prominent offering in Delphi, the Athenian treasury, at the very low level of the western side, namely very close to visitors climbing up.</p>

<p>Writing new documents on old monuments is a common secondary usage of Delphic monuments as many of large offerings offer perfect blanks in marble. Among all the 7 available Roman documents in Delphi, six were written on existing monuments (one on the Athenian treasury, two on the Paulus’ pillar, one on the orthostate of the temple), and two of them were even written on the same one, namely the honorific statue of M’ Acilius Glabrio. After the Delphians dedicated the equestrian statue to the Roman consul in -191, a letter from him to the city giving A long list of properties to the Delphians was inscribed right below the dedication, and its author was not named, suggesting that a careful reader would know who the author is. A year later, consul Livius Salinator wrote another letter about the assassination of Delphian embassy, which was inscribed alongside the previous letter. This time we do know the author and the topic both changed, but the authority of the Roman documents had already been materialised in the statue of the grand benefactor and imperator. As the two letters dealt with similar issues, it is reasonable to understand why the Delphian authorities chose to shorten Salinator’s letter and inscribe it onto the statue.</p>

<p>In short, for existing monuments, the anchor is clear: as the original location, size, and purpose were still known to many, especially to the Delphians, the reuse normally did not depart much from the original. In the case of the pillar, we see a strong political message conveyed in the practice of total capture and repurposing. The usage of the Latin texts also shows clearly visible Roman presence in the sanctuary, in contrast to the largely Greek landscape.</p>

<h2 id="landscape-a-gradual-change">Landscape: a gradual change</h2>

<p>Talking about the landscape, we observe a gradual change in the period between -190 and -31. In the late third century and the early second century BCE, the <em>epiphanestatos topoi</em> (most visible spaces) in Delphi are (1) the front terrace of the temple, where many of the large dedications from Hellenistic kings were found, following the famous serpent column celebrating the defeat of the Persians; (2) the <em>halos</em> in front of the Portico of the Athenians, where many ritual processions started or ended. Romans and Delphians all know that the disposition of offerings display a mini „politics of space“, so we see when Romans erected their dedications or when the Delphians dedicated statues for Roman officials, the statues were normally found at the aforementioned two areas. Among the 10 Roman monuments we found <em>in situ</em>, four were at the <em>halos</em> and six were at the temple terrace.</p>

<p>Especially important is the temple terrace, because the pillar, which could be seen later as the Roman <em>monument à souvenir</em>. All the monuments found at the <em>halos</em> predated the pillar, that’s to say, after Pydna, the Delphians dedicated statues for Roman officials only on the temple terrace. Only Eumenes II king of Pergamon and Prusias king of Bithynia have such prestige in the second century. Also, 48% of the Delphic dedications were made for Romans, making the temple terrace almost a space for the Romans. The practice was clearly understood by both Sulla and all the later Roman emperors, as dedications for Roman emperors in the Imperial time were almost all found on the terrace. Interestingly, such a clear transformation of the <em>epiphanestatos topos</em> did not happen in Olympia, as the Romans after the conquest of Achaia largely belittled Zeus’s sanctuary for a long time and only offered a small number of dedications there. The process only happens in the Imperial period, much later than the change in Delphi.</p>

<h3 id="praxeology">Praxeology</h3>

<p>Up to now, one may assume that the Romans and the Delphians all took great care of Roman monuments, as for the Delphians keeping them in good order can help them maintain a good relationship with the western dominant power. But this is somehow not true: like all the other monuments dedicated in Delphi, Roman ones were also open and Delphic authorities (the city and the Amphictiony) still held right to write other documents on them.</p>

<p>Let’s go back to the pillar. Archaeologists identified in total 39 texts on the pillar. You may have already noticed that below and above the Latin text for Paulus, we have Greek texts written later. The Delphians did put seven proxenia decrees for Romans on the pillar: this may be a deliberate choice by the honoured Romans, as two of the texts mentioned. In contrast to similar pillars like that of the Messenians or of Prusias, Paulus’s pillar has higher percentage of proxenia decrees for the honorand’s „compatriots“.</p>

<p>But we should not forget that the pillar was by nature a large white marble at the most visible space of the great sanctuary. Thus, when the Delphians felt the need to emphasise a crucial text or when someone wants his/her proxenia to be at a wonderful place, Paulus’ pillar is a good choice. On the orthostate base of the pillar to the left side, we find four long Amphictionic decrees solving a dispute between two neighbouring communities, Skarpheon and Thronion. The Athenians who oversaw the arbitration took great care of the issue and ordered the arbitration texts to be inscribed in the sanctuary. As an ally of the Romans, they may get permissions from the Romans or may think it’s no problem. Further in the last century BCE, 15 proxenia decrees for the Greeks were inscribed on the pillar: some were honoured because they served as ambassadors to Rome, but others have nothing to do with Rome. Moreover, we even find four manumission acts, and no link with Rome can be found.</p>

<p>The fact that these texts could be inscribed on the prominent pillar could only be understood within the common practice in this period. No monument in this period is »reserved« for a certain community, as the booming epigraphic practice boosted the demand of space for writing. Where there is a blank, there might be an inscription. At the same time, small texts like proxenia decrees and manumission acts tend to spread from the south to the north of the sanctuary: in mid-second century BCE, when most of the lower monuments near the entrance were almost full of texts, such texts start to appear on monuments on the temple terrace. The trend continued into early Imperial period, when such small texts occupied the previously uninscribed Northern theatre area.</p>

<p>Given the background of space usage in this period, we can say that the Roman monuments function as an integral part of the sanctuary and did not receive too much exceptional treatment. The Romans, who cared much about the erection of those monuments, did not exclude others from using their space: after all, »When in Delphi, do as what other people did here« may work during the entire life of a monument.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>»Connecting the new to the familiar«, the motto of the project Anchoring Innovation speaks a lot when I come to observe those early dedications by or for the Romans. Especially in Delphi where so many written and unwritten rules were familiar to local Delphians and the Amphictionians, it is important not only for the Romans but also for our later epigraphists to detect those rules, in order not to offer wayward and out-of-context interpretations.</p>

<p>In the classical period, Delphi was not dominated by any single power; in the Hellenistic time, the sanctuary was familiar with changing powers from the Macedonians to the Aitolians, from Pergamon to Athens. It is in the Roman period that we see a total dominance of imperial symbols and dedications. But I find it important to describe the change of such mechanisms, not only as a game of power display, but also a game of honour in exchange for favour. This will be a larger story to tell. Thank you for your attention.</p>]]></content><author><name>Wang Banban</name></author><category term="academic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a talk draft for a workshop at Universiteit Utrecht]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">數據庫檢索指南-Clauss-Slaby</title><link href="https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2021/LatinInscriptions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="數據庫檢索指南-Clauss-Slaby" /><published>2021-01-24T22:19:30+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-24T22:19:30+00:00</updated><id>https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2021/LatinInscriptions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://wangbanban17.github.io//blog/2021/LatinInscriptions/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a guide to using Latin epigraphy database, in CN]]></summary></entry></feed>